All right, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף Daf is כ"ב Chaf-beis
22. We pick up where do we pick up, Michael?
Three lines from the bottom of כ"א עמוד ב'. Chaf-alef amud-beis. אמר
רבי
אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב.
Amar Rabbi Abba
amar Rav Huna amar Rav.
Okay, can we make this in memory of...
certainly, certainly. Today is the funeral of Cantor Rosenblatt. I'm sorry what's
his first name? Phil. Phil Rosenblatt. Yeah.
פנחס Pinchas Rosenblatt. So it should be an עילוי iluy for his
נשמה. neshamah.
So we pick up three lines from the bottom on כ"א עמוד
ב'. Chaf-alef amud-beis. אמר רבי אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב. שלושה
שישבו לקיים את השטר. Amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav Huna amar Rav
sheloshah she-yashvu le-kayem es ha-shtar So we are since the overarching theme
is פה שאסר, peh she-asar, but one of the examples in the
משנה mishnah that we've been focusing on is the case of witnesses
who testify that it's their hand that it's their signature but then
there were some special circumstances that effectively invalidated it and therefore we're
now into a whole discussion about קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros and about
contradictory testimony and the like. So yesterday the last thing was about
a בית דין beis din that was going to validate a document
that was going to do a קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros and what
happens if two of the three recognize the signature and the third
does not and then when they're signing the document basically they have
to all three at that time recognize it cause that's what the
validation says, that's what the קיום kiyum says. So how's they get
the third one in the picture before they start to do the
validation. I should also by the way mention that the issue came
up yesterday about does it matter if they write the text well
at the time when the text is not yet accurate as long
as they wait to sign it. If the text says the three
of us recognize this signature, can they write that before signing it
or does the text have to be true at the time that
it's being written?
That was the issue right you dealt with at the end of
the day yesterday, which is interesting question because it comes on other
areas about מחזי כמזויף me-chazi ke-me-zuyaf like since the document only becomes
valid when it's signed can you pre-write a document if it's not
yet true and then wait for it to be true to sign
it. Like and this what? No, no, no, this is just a
technical issue because it's certainly going to be true when you sign
it. So for example by a כתובה kesubah a couple people have
a מנהג minhag that they don't write the קוף kuf of וקנינא,
ve-kanina, we the עדים eidus were קונה koneh like sort of from
the חתן chasan to obligate himself on all of this, they don't
write it until after the קנין, kinyan, they don't make the קוף
kuf in it because otherwise it's not yet true even though it's
not signed, so but they wanted they don't want it at the
time of its writing even before the time of its signing for
it not to be true. That picks up on a theme yesterday
of course the problem is that the whole darn thing isn't true
before the קוף kuf anyway until it's signed. First of all the
thing testifies to the fact that a wedding took place which hasn't
taken place yet. Because the signing of the כתובה kesubah takes place
before the wedding and the כתובה kesubah starts by saying on this
day so-and-so married this woman. That hasn't taken place yet. Right. Well,
okay, if we were ספרדי Sefardi we would do that. Но אשכנזים
Ashkenazim unfortunately who don't know what we're doing so we do it
early.
Anyway so it's an interesting issue like I never got why we're
so מקפיד makpid on the קוף kuf because the rest of the
document isn't true anyway and bottom line is what makes the document
valid is its signing not its being written. And I have to
tell you that more than once and I'm promising you I am
not the only one, I
sat when I'm being a מסדר קידושין, mesader kiddushin, right the witnesses
signed it before and I'd forgotten to have them first fill in
the leg of the line and make it into a קוף. kuf.
So
for many many years now just forgotten said forget that, I'm just
doing the whole וקנינא, ve-kanina, I'm not waiting to do the קנין
kinyan and then fill it in because it's more likely to make
a mistake that way. But that is I did want to mention
interesting in terms of an issue that comes up that we dealt
with yesterday about is this their concern of מחזי כשקרא me-chazi ke-shikra
when it's going to be accurate when you sign it but it's
not yet accurate and can you pre-write it at that stage. So
that was yesterday. We continue now today with issues of קיום שטרות
kiyum shtaros and the בית דין beis din what they have to
write in order to validate the document. So it says the following.
אמר רבי אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב Amar Rabbi Abba amar
Rav Huna amar Rav. שלושה שישבו לקיים את השטר Sheloshah she-yashvu le-kayem
es ha-shtar. וקרא ערער על אחד מהן v'kara irer al echad mehen
and one of
the
judges there
some type of a rumor some type of a challenge to his
validity has emerged. So עד שלא חתמו ad she-lo chasmu if they
have not yet validated the שטר shtar מעידים עליו me'idim alav the
other two can testify that this third guy. Valid, and then because
they're not נוגע בדבר Nogeia badavar yet, because they're not doing it
to defend their own signing of the שטר, Shtar, that hasn't happened.
If he wasn't valid, they'll ask him to step down and they'll
get a third person. So they're not really seen as נוגע בדבר.
Nogeia badavar. וחתים, Vechasim, and then they can sign it. משחתמו, Mishechasmu,
but if they've already signed the שטר, Shtar, so now their whole
testimony is being, you know, like thrown into, you know, and their
their status as a בית דין Beis Din having signed the שטר
Shtar is now being thrown into question, then they can no longer
testify on the third guy, it's like testifying on themselves. אין מעידים
עליו וחתים. Ein meidim alav vechasim. Then they cannot testify on him
and, you know, and and his signature.
Okay. So ערעור דמאי? Irur demai? What type of a challenge to
the validity of this third person? אי ערעור דגזלנותא, Ei irur degazlanusa,
if there are two people saying, you know, there's a challenge and
the challenge is understood to be that there are two witnesses that
are saying that this third guy is a גזלן, Gazlan, he has
some some reason he's really a פסול עד Pasul Eid and a
פסול דיין. Pasul Dayan. So תרי ותרי נינהו. Trei vesrei ninhu. So
just because the other two say he's not a גזלן, Gazlan, why
would that be good? It's two against two. What would make the
testimony of the other two on the בית דין? Beis Din? Like
you see the word ערעור Irur for us would have sounded not
like there's really testimony that he's invalid, but just some rumor, some,
you know, some type of a thing. But there's other גמרות Gemaros
that say that when it says ערעור Irur we should assume we're
talking that two people are actually saying this challenge. So if that's
true, how does the testimony of the other two counteract it, neutralize
it? אי ערעור דפגם משפחה, Ei irur depgam mishpacha, if it is
a challenge of a פגם משפחה Pgam mishpacha meaning that they're saying
that not like he's a גזלן Gazlan but saying like he's a
slave, you know, or some other type of a, I mean that
would be the most obvious that would make him not valid from
that perspective. Now you would say what difference does it make? You
know, if you're saying that the people raising the challenge are two
witnesses, it's always going to be two against two. But no, interestingly,
if it's a challenge about his personal status and something that's essentially
a matter of permanent record, not whether one time he stole something,
then גילוי מילתא בעלמא הוא. Gilui milsa be'alma hu.
Then the two that are saying that he's כשר, Kasher, it's what
you know, not only will they be believed, but what they, it's
not even considered like real עדות. Eidus. You know the way רש"י
Rashi says it is that because this is stuff that in the
end we're going to find out this information. Like is the guy
an עבד Eved or not? You know there's records about that, other
people know about that. It's not something that only two people will
know about. Now okay so fine, so what's the problem? That explains
it. People are saying he's a גזלן, Gazlan, these other two are
believed because it's something that's going to become obvious so there's more
believability on those that are saying that he's that he's not an
עבד. Eved. So רש"י Rashi says that then they would be believed
even after they had signed the document. Because you know the problem
about their נוגע בעדות Nogeia be'eidus would not really bother us so
much since this whole thing is a גילוי מילתא. Gilui milsa. Therefore
they would be in, if that were the issue, not that he
was being claimed to be a גזלן Gazlan but he was claimed
to be an עבד Eved or something of that nature, then the
other two would be believed even after they'd already signed the document.
If you look at the language of רש"י, Rashi, it says like
this. רש"י Rashi
says גילוי מילתא בעלמא Gilui milsa be'alma for the last of the
wide lines here. משחתמו אמאי אין מעידים Mishechasmu amai ein meidim even
after they signed why can't they testify that he's like not a
not an עבד? Eved? אלא מאי חשידא נוגע בעדות איכא? Ela mai
chashida nogeia be'eidus ika? Why are they considered that they are partial
to, you know, that they're a party to, that they're not impartial?
הכא דבר זה צריכים הם לברר ודבר עשוי לגלות הוא Hacha davar
zeh tzrichim hem levaver vedavar asui legalos hu שיבדקו אחריו עד שיתברר
הדבר Sheyivdeku achrav ad sheyisvarer hadavar ואין עיקרן של אלו תלוי בהגדתן.
Veein ikaran shel elu talui behagadan. It's not like it's really like
a type of their testimony. ואינן אלא מגלי דבר בעלמא. Veainan ela
megalei davar be'alma. They're just informing but they're not really being made
and you know eventually the information will be discovered. Of course the
funny thing is that the גילוי מילתא בעלמא Gilui milsa be'alma works
on both sides. So the people that are saying he is an
עבד Eved is also a גילוי מילתא בעלמא, Gilui milsa be'alma, right?
I mean somebody, whether you're claiming that he's כשר Kasher or he's
פסול, Pasul, if it's something that's a matter about his personal status
that we can all find out, it still doesn't explain why you
give more weight to those that say he's כשר Kasher than those
that are saying he's פסול. Pasul. Even though those that are saying
he's פסול Pasul you could say well, you know, they're not going
to lie because it's also a matter of public record and that'll
be discovered. So it's not so clear to me. But yes, but
maybe the point still is that it doesn't matter before or after
because we're not really dealing with עדות Eidus at that stage.
Yes. Well, one wouldn't understand is we had the whole discussion before
that oh yeah these guys who were חתומים על השטר chasumim al
hashtar but they were קטנים היו ketanim hayu or whatever. Why wouldn't
this discussion enter there? About גילוי מילתא? Gilui milsa? No, well, ask
their parents, I mean it's a גילוי מילתא. Gilui milsa.
Yeah, that's a good question. Yeah, I don't, right, why is the
question of the age less of a, but that was a question
of what they were at that stage, right? So how old were
they at that stage? I don't know, you know. I mean now
the guy could be in his 40s or 50s or whatever, you
know, how old was he? Nobody knows exactly how old he is
now, parents are dead. It's not the same. Here it's a question.
You're right, I think if it was a question that they're קטנים
ketanim right now that would be a גילוי מילתא, Gilui milsa, but
yeah.
Although one could speculate, I have no idea if this makes sense
or is you know true or not, but is could there be
a... Well, one could speculate, I have no idea if this makes
it true or not, but could there be a kind of transition
from completely oral genealogy testimony to some kind of written record
that's taken place?
So, it could be that.
So, how's that play out?
Well, if it's- if you end up relying on written records, then
the person, the עדים edim are not עדים, edim, they're just observers,
right?
But-
but again, the question is why are we assuming that there's more
written record? Yeah. Right. Which side of the equation? Right, right. But
you're just saying in terms of why it's גילוי מילתא giluy milsa
in terms of status. Yeah. I mean if פגם משפחה, pgam mishpacha,
I mean Rashi says it's an עבד. eved. I don't know... עבד,
eved, what type of עבד? eved?
Like an עבד עברי. eved Ivri. I mean not an עבד... Well
no, it would be an עבד כנעני eved Kenaani. though. No, an
עבד עברי eved Ivri wouldn't be possible, it would be an עבד
כנעני. Yeah. Yes, so again, I mean, why would it be- there
might be documentation about that. Right, right. Anyway, it's- again, it's not
clear to me why the גילוי מילתא giluy milsa clearly works on
one side of the equation here. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara wants
to know what's the scenario where you believe the two, but you
only believe them before they're נוגע בעדות. nogea b'eidus. So the גמרא
Gemara says, לעולם
אימא לך עיר דגזלנותא. le'olam eima lach ir d'gazlanusa. Fine. It's a
case where he's claimed- the third guy's claimed to be a גזלן.
gazlan. So why do you believe the second two? וקאמרי הני ידעינן
ביה דעבד תשובה. v'ka'amri hani yadeinan bei d'avad teshuvah. No, because they're
not contradicting the first two. They- yes, we do know that he
was a- he stole, but we also know that he did תשובה.
teshuvah. And therefore now he becomes a כשר עד. kasher eid. By
the way, this is fascinating in general. Well, yes, a כשר דיין,
kasher dayan, but the whole point is- and this is an interesting
discussion in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, you know.
It's like it comes up all- you know, sadly when people are
found,
rabbis or other people are found doing inappropriate, whatever, like in cases
about whether it's cases of abuse, whether it's cases about money issues
or other types of issues, and then they want to like be
reaccepted and they say, "Oh well, you know, I've done תשובה, teshuvah,
I apologize, I'm sorry." Often they don't actually apologize, they actually say,
"Mistakes were made," you know type of apology. But even if they
apologize, you know, what constitutes like תשובה? teshuvah? And it's important to
note that there are two types of תשובה. teshuvah. There's a תשובה
teshuvah that's between you and God. Between you and God, I don't
know, you could have done תשובה teshuvah a minute later and been
totally sincere about it and then I hope God forgives you, you
know. But that's not the תשובה teshuvah that's necessary for us in
terms of knowing that we can trust you again and in terms
of establishing your, you know, status in the community or in terms
of establishing your כשרות kashrus as an עד eid or your כשרות
kashrus as a דיין. dayan. So there we see in סנהדרין Sanhedrin
that there has to be something much more concrete. You know, not
only does it have to be rectifying things like returning money that
was stolen or whatever, but it has to be very concrete evidence
that we see that this person has changed their ways. It's not
just an internal process that they regretted and they've done תשובה teshuvah
between them and God. So that's an important discussion which we'll see
more when we get to- eventually when we get to סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
but it's not just like, "Oh you know, we saw him klopping
על חטא, al cheit, he was very frum in שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh
Esrei, so we know he's done תשובה." teshuvah. Something- you know, it
has to be something that really re-establishes his כשרות kashrus as a
דיין. dayan. Okay, but it's not contradicting the first two witnesses and
therefore the second testimony is also believed. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi
Zeira, הני מאותה דאמר רבי אבא שמיע לי. hani m'osa d'amar Rabbi
Abba shemia li. So says Rabbi Zeira, the following thing I heard
from Rabbi Abba, ואי לאו רבי אבא דמן עכו דאדכרן שכחתיה. v'ee
lav Rabbi Abba d'min Akko d'adkran shakachtiah. And if it had not
been that Rabbi Abba from Akko had reminded me about it, I
would have forgotten it. Of course reminds us of the discussion the
other day about forgetting a testimony and then somebody reminds you and
makes you remember what you had always known. So, interesting echo of
that. ג' שיושבו לקיים את השטר, Gimmel sheyashvu l'kayem es hashtar, three
people sat to a בית דין beis din to validate a document.
ומת אחד מהם, u'meis echad meihem, and one of them died before
they actually got around to signing it. So the three as a
בית דין beis din had seen the document and validated it, but
now it's time to sign it and only two of them are
around. So צריכים למכתב, tzrichim l'michtav, they have to write on the
document: במושב תלתא הוינא, b'moshav tlasa havina, we were in a מושב
moshav of שלושה, sheloshah, we were in a sitting of three, in
a, you know, three of us came together as a בית דין.
beis din. וחד ליתוהי, v'chad laysohei, and one is no longer among
us, one has died and that's why you're only going to see
two signatures on this document. It's sort of like the brothers and
יוסף, Yosef, right? ואחד איננו. v'echad einenu. So אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק- Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak so the reason they have to
do that- no, because the three had already seen it. Now they
get a third, they have to start the whole process again.
But can't you have like two of them testify and get it...
I guess, but okay, who needs to do that? Just sign the
darn document, okay. So anyway, so- but the point is, the reason
you have to do that is if you don't do that, people
will think that it was only two people who validated and it
won't be testimony that there was three people that validated it. You
have to know that it was a בית דין beis din that
validated it. You have to know that they were a בית דין
beis din saying that they were three. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק,
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, וכתב דא שטר דנן נפק לקדמנא, v'chasav
dei shtar denan nafak l'kadmana, if they write by- this is all
very fascinating of course, because they're not just making up this language,
right? You get a sense that these things that we're seeing here
are type of the, you know, technical legal like language that was
used on these
קיום שטרות.
kiyuum shtaros. Exactly. שטר דנן נפק לקדמנא, Shtar denan nafak l'kadmana, the
following document was presented to us, בי דינא, bei dina, we the
בית דין. beis din. And then they sign it. תו לא צריך,
Tu lo tzarich, then you don't have to write anything else because
then even though there's only two signatures, they're saying that they were
a בית דין beis din and they're saying they were a בית
דין beis din saying that they were three. Okay, so you don't
have to explicitly say we were three. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, ודילמא בי דינא דחצפא הוי? v'dilma bei dina d'Chatzpa havei? Who?
Maybe it
was... insolent, insolent בית דין Beit Din meaning they're not supposed to
be a בית דין Beit Din of three but according to at
least שמואל Shmuel of two, but according to at least שמואל Shmuel
it's possible. Okay. וכהדשמואל U'chedeShmuel דאמר שמואל d'amar Shmuel שנים שדנו דיניהם
דין shnayim shedanu dineihem din אלא שנקראו בית דין חצוף. ela shenikrau
beit din chatzuf.
If two did it, they would be considered a בית דין, Beit
Din, it would be valid except that they would be as like
an insolent or brazen בית דין. Beit Din. And if that were
true, we would want to know that because maybe we, although שמואל
Shmuel accepts a בית דין Beit Din of two, maybe we wouldn't.
So just because it says בית דין, Beit Din, maybe we can't
really trust that בית דין Beit Din means three. So maybe we
shouldn't accept the language of בית דין Beit Din if we only
see two signatures. You know, yes, it says בית דין, Beit Din,
but it has two signatures, so maybe we should still worry that
maybe there were only two of them and not three of them.
Maybe you explicitly have to say three. So the גמרא Gemara says:
No, דכתב ביה, dichtav bei, it doesn't just say בית דין. Beit
Din. Now we're going to change what we said before. It says
בי דינא דרבנא אשי, bei dina d'Rabbana Ashi, the בית דין Beit
Din of רב אשי. Rav Ashi. So this was like רב אשי
Rav Ashi was the רב Rav of מתא מחסיא Mata Mechasya when
and therefore like it was sort of saying like, you know, the
בית דין Beit Din of the, we the, as members of the
בית דין Beit Din of the city, you know,
the, so they're clearly no, everything's going to be done correctly if
you're part of like the official בית דין Beit Din of the
city. So we don't have to worry you're only a בית דין
Beit Din of two. So the גמרא Gemara says: ודילמא רבנן דבי
רב אשי כדשמואל סבירא להו? U'dilma Rabbanan d'bei Rav Ashi k'Shmuel sevira
lehu? How do you know? Maybe even the, maybe even the rabbis
that are part of the whole בית דין Beit Din system of
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, maybe they also felt that they could just
do two. It's funny because even if they פסק'נד paskened like שמואל,
Shmuel, you could assume that they weren't going to do a בדיעבד
bedi'avad בית דין. Beit Din. But again, maybe the fact that there's
only two signatures should make us worried about that.
So the גמרא Gemara says: דכתב ביה, dichtav bei, fine, what's written
in it is ואמר לנא רבנא אשי. v'amar lana Rabbana Ashi. רב
אשי Rav Ashi told us to sit as a בית דין. Beit
Din. So רב אשי Rav Ashi never would have approved of a
בית דין Beit Din sitting that was two rather than three. Of
course, once you say that, you might as well just write there
were three of us. You know? It starts by saying if you
say בית דין, Beit Din, you don't have to say three. Now
it tells you, oh, you have to say בית דין, Beit Din,
you have to say we were the official בית דין Beit Din
of the city and רב אשי Rav Ashi told us to go
ahead and sign. All right. Anyway, fine. But that is the end
of that discussion in terms of a בית דין Beit Din and
קיום שטרות, kiyuum shtarot, but we are not done. We are still
within this world
of הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar and its intersection with the world of
עדות. eidus. So let's take a look. Yes.
Is there sort of an underlying similarity with the עדים זוממין eidim
zomemin sort of logic, like two others come by and you favor
one over the other?
Yeah, I mean, we had that before. I mean, we dealt with
זימום zimmum and saying פסול pasul and all that thing. Yeah, I
mean, so that's relevant, but when it's not עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim,
then it's a little more complicated, right? Who do you believe? I
mean, in עדים זוממים eidim zomemim at least you know what the
rules are. You just have to understand why it's true that you
believe the later ones. All right. So האשה שאמרה, Ha'ishah she'amra, אשת
איש הייתי, eshet ish hayiti, so a woman said that I was
married, וגרושה אני, ugrushah ani, but now I am divorced, נאמנת, ne'emenet,
she's believed. I mean, she's believed that now she can, you know,
marry somebody. She's, she's assumed to be available to be married. Since
הפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר, ha'peh she'asar hu ha'peh she'hitir, the same
mouth that made her forbidden on other men when she said she
was married made her permissible that she says that now she's divorced.
ואם יש עדים שהיתה אשת איש, Ve'im yesh eidim she'haitah eshet ish,
however if there were witnesses, והיא אומרת גרושה אני, ve'hi omeret grushah
ani, and she said yes, I was married, but now I'm divorced,
אינה נאמנת, einah ne'emenet, she's not believed. So this is a straight
הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar type of a case. שבייתי וטהורה אני, Shivity
ut'horah ani, she said that I was taken captive but I was
not raped, because we generally assume that a woman taken captive was
raped, and therefore had she been married to a כהן, Kohen, she
would now be forbidden to her husband the כהן. Kohen. So אינה
נאמנת, einah ne'emenet, she's not believed, הפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר... ha'peh
she'asar hu ha'peh she'hitir... I'm sorry, נאמנת. ne'emenet. I'm sorry. נאמנת. Ne'emenet.
I skipped down. Right. נאמנת. Ne'emenet. She is believed. הפה שאסר הוא
הפה שהתיר. Ha'peh she'asar hu ha'peh she'hitir. The same thing that we,
we only know she's taken captive because of her own words, so
she's also believed that she was not raped. ואם יש עדים שנשבית,
Ve'im yesh eidim shenishbeit, and if there are witnesses that she was
taken captive, והיא אומרת טהורה אני, ve'hi omeret tehorah ani, and she
says that I am still pure, I have not been raped, אינה
נאמנת, einah ne'emenet, she's not believed. ואם משניסת באו עדים, Ve'im misheniseit
bau eidim, but if however she got married and then witnesses came,
now exactly which case is this going on? Because in the case
about being taken captive, presumably that's the problem because she's already married
to a כהן. Kohen. But whatever, maybe it's the first case. Let's
say it's the first case about the question that she says that
she's divorced. So there had been witnesses that she was married prior,
she claimed she was divorced, so she's not believed because we, that's
the, you need testimony that she's divorced if we've established by witnesses
that she's been married. But she went ahead and she, the witnesses
that said she had been married prior only showed up after she
had married this guy, the second guy. הרי זו לא תצא, Harei
zu lo tetzei, in that case we do not force her to
get divorced. So we will see about that. That's already something new
that we haven't discussed in the הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar because here
you're dealing with הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar about personal status. So it's
not just a question about money or other types of issues and
there we have to wonder like how far are we going to
go in order to make her, you know, break up a current
marriage
if now that after the fact we have found that there were
witnesses. Michael, you had a question?
Yeah, I mean, because getting back to the captive thing, I thought
we generally, I thought we even encountered this before, that you assume
that she was raped and then you wouldn't.
Yeah, so it's true, I mean, we do tend to assume that,
but if we independently establish it, it is a question, as we've
said before, about how much when you say הפה שאסר Hapeh She'asar
would you believe the second part of the statement if there's presumptions
to assume that that type of thing never happened? Like the גמרא
Gemara sort of said, well, if they say yes, it's our signatures
but we were
קטנים, Ketanim, there's the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that you
don't believe the second part of the statement, even though you have
a הפה שאסר, Hapeh She'asar, because we assume that קטנים Ketanim will
never sign documents. So you could in theory say, even if I
generally accept הפה שאסר, Hapeh She'asar, I can't believe that a woman
was taken captive without being raped. Okay, but the משנה Mishnah isn't
assuming that. That was like a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position, you
know, at least before by עדים, Edim, one way of understanding
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. All right, so what you're raising is a
different question, which is, let's say there are witnesses that she was
captive, but let's say there are circumstantial evidence. Right? So that also
gets to a גמרא Gemara before about how is הפה שאסר Hapeh
She'asar different than מיגו? Migo? רש״י Rashi says הפה שאסר Hapeh She'asar
is that the person
is just offering up this information without any prompting. תוספות Tosafot says,
no, הפה שאסר Hapeh She'asar could still be responding to a challenge
and a claim, but it's different than מיגו Migo because there's nothing
concrete evidence, not שור שחוט לפניך Shor Shachut Lefanecha that has to
be explained away. So there could be a case where it could
be a שור שחוט לפניך Shor Shachut Lefanecha and it could be
more of a מיגו Migo and less of a הפה שאסר Hapeh
She'asar and then it would be less believable if the logic would
go against it. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רבי אסי,
Amar Rabbi Assi, now we've been dealing with the last I don't
know how many, six דף Daf or something, or more, with הפה
שאסר, Hapeh She'asar, now finally the גמרא Gemara introduces this question of
the basis for it. אמר רבי אסי, Amar Rabbi Assi, מניין להפה
שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר? Minayin L'hapeh She'asar Hu Hapeh Shehitir? Where do
you know that the mouth that makes forbidden is the mouth that
makes permissible? Maybe you also mean specifically in an issue of personal
status. Okay, a lot of the issues we've been dealing before were
money-related. Even the question about whether the woman was a בתולה, Betulah,
which was about her physical status or whatever, was about a question
of money. Here it's about a question of איסור, Issur, right? About
is she forbidden to other men or not, and so on. So
how do you know this?
מן התורה? Min HaTorah? Where do you know it from the תורה?
Torah? שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק Pasuk says, את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה
לאשה. Et Biti Natati La'ish Hazeh L'isha. This man... this daughter I
gave to this man as a wife, לאשה, L'isha, excuse
me. לאיש, La'ish, when the father says I gave my daughter to
this man, אסרה, Asrah, he made her forbidden on the whole world,
because he didn't say yet which man. So he said I'm marrying
off my daughter, so now she's forbidden to everybody. הזה, Hazeh, and
then he says "this man," התירה, Hetirah, I made her permissible to
that man. So you see the same mouth that made her forbidden
to everybody is believed to say which man she's permissible to. Now,
of course, if that were your only basis, you would say maybe
it's all when it's literally like the... I mean, that's the same
sentence, it's the same statement, it's the same event. Right? Even if
a woman says נשביתי וטהורה אני, Nishbeiti Ut'horah Ani, אשת איש הייתי,
Eshet Ish Hayiti, and now I'm
a גרושה, Gerushah, so grammatically it's the same sentence, but you're actually
testifying to two different things, right? You might be saying two different
things in one sentence, but you're saying two different things. Here it
is the exact same statement, it is clarifying what you meant when
you said לאיש. La'ish. So anyway, as a basis for
הפה שאסר, Hapeh She'asar, that does not seem that that's too generalizable.
Nevertheless, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So למה לי קרא? Lamah Li Kra? So the גמרא Gemara says,
you don't even really need a פסוק Pasuk anyway for הפה שאסר
Hapeh She'asar and that, it's questionable what that פסוק Pasuk would have
done with it, but you don't need a פסוק. Pasuk. סברא, Sevara,
it's just logical. הוא אסר הוא התיר. Hu Asar Hu Hetir. He
made her forbidden, in the case of the father and the daughter,
he made her permissible. Like, it's just logical, like if you're going
to believe part of my statement, you should believe the whole part.
So yes?
Do you understand the דרשה Derashah that they're trying to make here?
Because it's so
faulty.
Yeah, I know, I understand. That's why I pointed it out. Okay,
אלא, Ella, doesn't matter, the גמרא Gemara rejects it. אלא, Ella, fine,
we know it from סברא Sevara anyway. All right, it's all סברא.
Sevara. That's okay.
אלא כי אצטריך קרא לכדרב הונא. Ella Ki Itzterich Kra L'chiderav Huna.
You're right. הפה שאסר Hapeh She'asar we know from סברא. Sevara. So
everything we've been talking about the last week, הפה שאסר, Hapeh She'asar,
it's all סברא, Sevara, which of course we've pretty much been assuming
anyway. Okay, so what do you need the פסוק Pasuk for? כי
אצטריך לכדרב הונא, Ki Itzterich L'chiderav Huna, like רב הונא אמורא, Rav
Huna Amora, רב, Rav, דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, De'amar Rav Huna
Amar Rav, מניין לאב שנאמן לאסור את בתו מן התורה? Minayin L'av
Shene'eman Le'esor Et Bito Min HaTorah? How do you know a father
is believed to say... forget the התיר Hetir part, how do you
know a father is believed to say who he married his daughter
off to? Okay, and that she would be treated as an אשת
איש Eshet Ish as a result of it. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it
says,
את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה, Et Biti Natati La'ish Hazeh, so I
gave my daughter over to this man and presumably he's believed. Now
of course, that doesn't actually prove that he's believed because in the
context in the תורה, Torah, it's a context about מוציא שם רע,
Motzi Shem Ra, right? The guy says your daughter wasn't a virgin
and they fight the whole thing out. So nobody is debating whether
she was married. So there's no proof... it's not clear in the
פסוקים Psukim in the תורה Torah that we're relying on the father's
testimony... The father is there to say that she was actually a
virgin and this man is making up false rumors about my daughter,
but somehow because the תורה Torah frames it that the father makes
this declaration, the גמרא Gemara understands that from here we see that
not only does he have the power to do that, but that
he is believed to do that.
So that's number, so that's what we learn from that. So now
the גמרא Gemara says הזה למה לי? Hazeh lamah li? To remember
before we were focusing also on the word הזה. hazeh. So to
tell you like he could say which man? So what do you
need הזה hazeh to tell you since you don't need it to
tell you פה שאסר, peh she'asar, that we know from סברא? sevara?
So מיבעי ליה לכדתניא רבי יונה, miba'ei lei le'chi de'tanya Rabbi Yona,
we need it for what רבי יונה Rabbi Yona teaches. To תניא
רבי יונה, tanya Rabbi Yona, את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה, Es bitti
natatti la'ish hazeh, I gave my daughter to this man. הזה, hazeh,
this man, ולא ליבם, velo leyavam, not to the brother-in-law. What does
that mean? It means that in the הלכות halachos of מוציא שם
רע, motzi shem ra, which is going to be a פרק perek
we're going to get up to in כתובות, Kesuvos, okay, if the
brother-in-law is the one that spreads false repute about the woman, says,
yeah, my brother married this woman and she wasn't a virgin, okay,
so okay, he's not the husband, so the laws of מוציא שם
רע motzi shem ra does not apply then. Even if he's lying,
he's not subject to the same fines and punishment as a מוציא
שם רע motzi shem ra because he's not the actual husband himself.
All right, so that's and we don't believe him either, we don't
do anything about it.
Yeah, anyway, but that's so that's just a parenthetical statement about מוציא
שם רע. motzi shem ra. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, back to our
case of our משנה. Mishnah. האישה שאמרה אשת איש אני וחזרה ואמרה
פנויה אני. ha'isha she'amra eshes ish ani ve'chazra ve'amra penuyah ani. A
woman, now we are going to get into a new category, not
פה שאסר, peh she'asar, but retracting. And remember we said that witnesses
are not believed to retract, right? We say כיון שהגיד שוב אינו
חוזר ומגיד. keivan she'higid shuv eino chozer umaggid. But now we're going
to deal with a person who makes an assertion and retracting their
own statement, not as a witness, and they'll have an explanation why
it was that they are retracting. Let's take a look. האישה שאמרה,
ha'isha she'amra, so אשת איש אני, eshes ish ani, first she went
around saying she was married. וחזרה ואמרה פנויה אני, ve'chazra ve'amra penuyah
ani, and then she said actually I'm single. נאמנת, ne'emenes, she's believed.
והוא, ve'hu, so the גמרא Gemara says, she's believed? ושוויא לנפשה חתיכא
דאיסורא, ve'shavya l'nafsheh chaticha de'issura, she made herself a forbidden object, she
basically went ahead and declared she was married, and that we take,
for example, the reason it was a חידוש chiddush that the father's
believed about his daughter is because he's not saying something about himself,
right? We've taken for granted that if somebody says something about their
own personal status and it's sort of, and it makes themselves forbidden,
you know, they're not believed to say I got divorced if they
had been married, but they would be believed to go around and
say I'm married and make it forbidden for anybody to marry them,
okay, because that's the principle of שוויא לנפשה חתיכא דאיסורא, shavya l'nafsheh
chaticha de'issura, you know, you've made a declaration that you're forbidden and
therefore we accept your statement against yourself. We don't accept your statement
to benefit yourself, but we accept your statement to restrict yourself, we
accept it against yourself. So the גמרא Gemara says once you said
she was married, that makes us assume, take her at her word,
that she is married because that's a restrictive statement. So how can
now we believe to change that? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רב אמר רב הונא כגון שנתנה אמתלא לדבריה, amar Rav amar Rav
Huna k'gon she'nasna amatla l'devareha, she gave an explanation for her words.
She explained why she had been saying she was
married,
okay, and then we
will believe. So a person is believed to retract an earlier statement.
It's not, remember by the way, a statement in court, okay, and
it's not like עדות, eidus, but it's
a statement
that for various purposes is believed, but they're believed also then to
retract it if they give a reasonable explanation. And now we're going
to have an example of that. Well, before let's take a look.
I mean, either one is right. One that explains why we should
believe the second part of the statement, the second one is now
true. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we've done a ברייתא. Braisa.
תניא נמי הכי אמרה אשת איש אני
וחזרה ואמרה פנויה אני אינה נאמנת,
tanya nami hachi amra eshes ish
ani
ve'chazra ve'amra penuyah ani eina ne'emenes, fundamentally she is not believed. אבל
אם נתנה אמתלא לדבריה נאמנת, aval im nasna amatla l'devareha ne'emenes, she
is believed.
ומעשה נמי, uma'aseh nami, there was a story באישה אחת גדולה שהייתה
גדולה בנוי, be'ishah achas gedolah she'hayesa gedolah benoy, there was a certain
adult, presumably the first גדולה gedolah here means an adult woman, because
then it's not an issue about her father marrying her off, okay,
so she was and that she was of exceedingly beautiful וקפצו לה
בני אדם לקדשה ve'kaftzu lah bnei adam l'kadshah and everybody wanted to
marry her. So ואמרה להם מקודשת אני, ve'amra lahem mekudeshes ani, I'm
married, לימים, li'yamim, stop bothering me. לימים עמדה וקידשה עצמה, li'yamim amda
ve'kidsha atzmah, then a little while later she went ahead and she
married herself off, okay, that's why she's a גדולה, gedolah, her father
didn't marry her off, she married off, and that's why she had
to defend her own, herself. Her father wasn't able to chase off
the suitors, okay. אמרו לה חכמים, amaru lah chachamim, so the sages
said to her מה ראית לעשות כן? mah ra'is la'asos ken? So
why did you do this? First you said you were married. אמרה
להם, amra lahem, she said to them בתחילה שבאו אלי אנשים שאינם
הגונים, batchilah she'ba'u elai anashim she'einam hagunim, first I was getting improper
suitors, אמרתי מקודשת אני, amarti mekudeshes ani, I said I'm married. עכשיו
שבאו אלי אנשים הגונים, achshav she'ba'u elai anashim hagunim, now that proper
suitors have come to, you know, to propose to me, אמרתי וקידשתי
את עצמי, amarti ve'kidash-ti es atzmi, I went and I married myself
off. Of course, you wonder why the people persevered thinking that she
was married. How could anybody be a proper suitor if she's telling
them she's married? But then maybe she went
somewhere no, but then
how does the הגונים hagunim come along if she's been telling everybody
she's maybe she went to a different town I don't know. Anyway
it's permissible for a woman to lie in order to avoid the
wrong kind of man. There you go exactly. So. But I mean
the גמרא Gemara in general, I mean you should know that, you
know, even with like, you know, מדבר שקר תרחק midvar sheker tirchak
and all of that, the גמרא Gemara never takes the position certainly
against like white lies. I mean the גמרא Gemara even explicitly says
that it's מותר לשנות מפני השלום, mutar lishanot mipnei hashalom, but even
in terms of like the הלכה halacha of מדבר שקר תרחק, midvar
sheker tirchak, halachically that's in the context of, you know, בית דין.
beis din. It's not in the context of like, you know, so
the גמרא Gemara certainly does take is not at all censures the
idea of what she's doing, that actually seems seems to feel it's
pretty reasonable, okay, and she's believed. Okay, וזו הלכה הורה רב אחא
שר הבירה לפני חכמים באושא, ve-zo halacha horah Rav Acha sar habira
lifnei hachamim be-Usha, and this was the הלכה halacha that רב אחא,
Rav Acha, the I don't know, the master of the castle, whatever
that means, שושן הבירה Shushan Habira or whatever, there you go, that's
right in the פורים Purim context. Anyway, he brought before the חכמים
hachamim in אושא, Usha, ואמרו ve-amru and they said אם נתנה אמתלא
לדבריה, im natna amatla l'devareha, so presumably so maybe he asked them
what the ruling was on this particular case. Anyway, they said if
she gave a reasonable explanation for her words, נאמנת, ne'emenet, she is
believed. Okay, בעא מיניה שמואל מרב, ba'ei minei Shmuel me-Rav, so שמואל
Shmuel asked רב. Rav. אמרה טמאה אני וחזרה ואמרה טהורה אני, amra
temei'ah ani ve-chazra ve-amra tehorah ani, a woman tells her husband I'm
a נדה, niddah, and then she says actually I'm not a נדה.
niddah. So מהו, mahu, what's the story? אמר ליה אף בזו, amar
lei af be-zo, even in this case, אם נתנה אמתלא לדבריה נאמנת,
im natna amatla l'devareha ne'emenet, if she gives a reasonable explanation she
is believed. תנא מיניה ארבעים זמנין, tana minei arba'im zimnin, he learned
it from him forty times, said really, she's believed? Anyway, forty times
he said yes, she's believed. ואפילו הכי לא עבד שמואל עובדא בנפשיה,
ve-afilo hachi lo avad Shmuel uvda be-nafshei, and even though שמואל Shmuel
was not prepared to actually פסקן pasken on this, it's an interesting
phrase, he wasn't willing to פסקן pasken for himself on this, and
if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, so look at תוספות
Tosfos ואפילו הכי עבד שמואל עובדא בנפשיה לא עבד. afilo hachi avad
Shmuel uvda be-nafshei lo avad. He says פירוש, peirush, he says ר''ח
Rach הביא ירושלמי, heivi Yerushalmi, שמואל בעא לאזדקוקי לאיתתיה, Shmuel ba'ei le-izdakukei
le-ittetei, so שמואל Shmuel wanted to have sex with his wife. אמרה
ליה, amra lei, she said to him, טמאה אני, temei'ah ani, I'm
a נדה. niddah. ולמחר, ule-machar, the next day, אמרה טהורה אני, amra
tehorah ani, she says I'm not, it doesn't change in a day,
right? You need at least a week. So even if you're, you
know, even if you're going on the before חומרא דרבי זירא. chumra
de-Rabbi Zeira. Anyway, so אמר לה amar lah he said to her,
אתמול טמאה יומא דיין טהורה? etmol temei'ah yoma dein tehorah? Yesterday you
were a נדה niddah today you're טהורה? tehorah? So אמרה ליה amra
lei she said to him, אתמול לא הוה בי חילא כי האי
שעתא. etmol lo havi bi cheila ki ha-hi sha'ata. So yesterday I
didn't have the strength to have sex, so this was a way
of saying no. So so אזל שמואל לקמיה דרב, azal Shmuel lekamei
de-Rav, so he went and asked רב, Rav, ואמר ליה ve-amar lei
he said אם נתנה אמתלא לדבריה נאמנת, im natna amatla l'devareha ne'emenet,
if she gives a reasonable explanation she is believed. So this is
actually quite interesting, you know, because some sociologists have found or whatever
people that have talked to women who keep, you know, הלכות נדה,
hilchos niddah, different types of attitudes people who keep it, that some
women find in some ways that it's very empowering because הלכה halacha
actually gives them the ability to say no to their husband, you
know, which I mean, having a headache is not enough. Exactly. Well
let's face it, I mean, you know, it's often it's not enough
just in terms of the way that, you know, interpersonal dynamics works
and certainly in patriarchal societies women very it was very rare that
women would have a voice to actually say no, you know. So
there's a, so and this is really very surprising because it's one
thing to say, okay, you know, fine, you're believed, but then you
gotta you gotta be treat yourself as a נדה niddah for a
whole week, you know, there's significant consequences. This actually is amazing, right?
The woman could say could if she felt that she couldn't say
no, she could use this to say no and then she could
say the next day I actually was making it up, of course
then one wonders how that's going then play out in the future
when she says that she's a נדה, niddah, you know, which raises
interesting questions, which might be why שמואל Shmuel was sort of like
resisting this because it's not the same as a woman who says
I'm married and then she says I'm divorced, right? I'm not married,
I was never married, I was saying it to chase people off.
This is like an ongoing real that's like a thing like it
that like it's like that was like a certain like a one-time
event, right, exactly. This is like an ongoing type of a thing
within the marriage and it's also number one, number two, and how
is that going to play out in terms of the ongoing dynamics,
and number two is is that it's completely reasonable that she did
become a נדה, niddah, right, even if it's not during her her
normal cycle, like sometimes women have breakthrough bleeding and the whole thing,
so, you know, you might be more suspicious of the retraction, right,
because, you know, who knows, maybe she was a נדה niddah and
now she actually wants to go, you know, wants to have sex
and wants to avoid the consequence of like, you know, the circumstances
that it's possible that that she actually
had become a נדה niddah are not unlikely. So that seems to
explain what some of the resistance here was to believe it, but
at the end of the day that's the הלכה, halacha, a woman
says she's a נדה niddah and the next day she says I
actually was just making up a story, if it's if it's a
reasonable explanation she's believed, but you understand why this is a bigger
חידוש chidush than the earlier part of the גמרא. Gemara. Instead of,
you know, I thought of a נדה niddah then I, you know,
but then I looked more closely and then I realized it wasn't.
Right, so you're saying the אמתלא, amatla, there could be a better
אמתלא amatla rather than like as opposed to a person couldn't have
been mistakenly thinking that she was married, but she could have made
a mistake and then, yeah, I finally went and I showed the
בדיקה bedika cloth to the רב Rav and he said it wasn't
a problem, that's true. Okay, so that אמתלא amatla makes... maybe is
more believable but there are cases where, you know again like so,
so that presumably is why it wasn't so פשוט pashut to apply
the idea of אמתלא, amatla, you know, to this case because the
נדה niddah case could easily be, you know, depending on what the
circumstances are, more or less believable than the other case. All right,
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Very important הלכות halachot we're learning today. שנים
אומרים מת ושנים אומרים לא מת. Shnayim omrim met v'shnayim omrim lo
met. Two people say that the, that, the husband died, reminding us
back of יבמות, Yevamot, question about the guy who's overseas, what happened
to him. Two people say he died, two people say he didn't
die. שנים אומרים מת ושנים אומרים לא מת. Shnayim omrim met v'shnayim
omrim lo met. שנים אומרים נתגרשה ושנים אומרים לא נתגרשה. Shnayim omrim
nitgarsha v'shnayim omrim lo nitgarsha. Two say that the women got divorced
and two say she didn't get divorced. הרי זו לא תינשא. Harei
zo lo tinnasei. The woman can't marry another person, man, because you
know it's a contradictory testimony, so she's still presumed to be a
married woman. ואם נישאת לא תצא, V'im nissat lo tetzei, but if
she married, she doesn't have to get divorced. הגמרא Hagemara is going
to challenge that in a minute. I mean if it's contradictory testimony
and we have a status of being a married woman, why is
she allowed to stay married to the second guy? רבי מנחם ברבי
יוסי אומר תצא. Rabbi Menachem bar Rabbi Yossi omer tetzei. Rabbi Menachem
bar Rabbi Yossi says no, she does have to get divorced from
the second guy because the witnesses neutralized one another. אמר רבי מנחם
ברבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Menachem bar Rabbi Yossi. Said Rabbi Menachem bar
Rabbi Yossi, אימתי אני אומר תצא? Eimatai ani omer tetzei? When do
I say she has to divorce the second guy? בזמן שבאו עדים
ואחר כך נישאת. Bizman shebau edim v'achar kach nissat. If they were
neutralized before she got married. Okay, so therefore by you know so
she shouldn't marry the second guy. She had a status of an
אשת איש eishet ish and the two witnesses and the two sets
of witnesses had contradicted one another. אבל נישאת ואחר כך באו עדים.
Aval nissat v'achar kach bau edim. If there was one set of
witnesses that the husband died, one set of witnesses that she got
divorced, and then she got married to another guy, and then witnesses
came to neutralize it. In that case, ואחר כך באו עדים לא
תצא. v'achar kach bau edim lo tetzei. She does not have to,
which sort of echoes our משנה, mishnah, right, about when witnesses came
later she would not have to get divorced. Then maybe she has
a status of קול kol about being married to the current guy.
All right, so let's take a look. We're going to start first
with the case of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that says that
she shouldn't get married when the witnesses have have contradicted, but if
she does she doesn't have to get divorced. So and that's even
after the witnesses came. If she married the second guy she doesn't
have to get divorced. So why not, says the גמרא. Gemara. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look.
תרי ותרי נינהו. Trei v'trei ninhu. It's two against two. הבא על
הבא אשם תלוי קאי. Haba al haba asham talui ka'ei. Any man
that would have sex with this woman—two witnesses said the husband died
and two said he didn't—any man, so she's a ספק אשת איש.
safek eishet ish. Any man that would have sex with her and
she herself that would have sex with any man would have to
bring a an אשם תלוי, asham talui, a חטאת chatat that's brought,
an אשם asham that's brought for a doubtful איסור כרת issur karet
because she might be an אשת איש eishet ish and sleeping with
another man, it could be an איסור דאורייתא. issur d'Oraita. So if
now that we have this, how, and if anything also she has
a חזקה chazaka of being an אשת איש. eishet ish. So how
could we say that בדיעבד b'diavad she could stay married to the
second guy? So אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, כגון שנישאת לאחד
מעידיה. k'gon shenissat l'echad me'edeiha. No, she's marrying the one of the
witnesses that says that he saw the husband die or the witness
that says she saw her get a גט. get. So that man,
we had this before, so that man is saying I know that
the guy is dead. It might be that everybody else says there's
contradictory witnesses and for an outside person you're saying I have no
base you know I have to assume that the husband might still
be alive. Okay but I personally know that the husband is dead
so I'm comfortable going ahead and doing this. And if you know,
and now the question of this raises, we're going to get to
her in a minute, but the interesting question that comes up of
course is about you know what's the role of בית דין Beit
Din in this, right? You know we tend often to think about
like we don't tend often to divide between בית דין Beit Din
in terms of thinking about like you know secular civil law and
religious and then religious law. We tend to think like בית דין
Beit Din is controlling everything. You know but on the other hand,
it's like this is not something that you could give anybody מלקות
malkot for because it's a ספק. safek. The only consequence about this
within the you know in our world, besides between the person and
God, is the bringing of a קרבן, korban, right? The bringing of
a קרבן korban is something that again is the person's own. How
בית דין Beit Din as a general rule does not force people
to bring a קרבן חטאת korban chatat or a קרבן אשם korban
asham because that's about their own כפרה. kapara. It might force them
to bring other קרבנות korbanot they're חייב chayav for but not something
that's about their own כפרה. kapara. So basically at the end of
the day, even though בית דין Beit Din tends to also be
overseeing religious issues and not just civil issues, this at the end
of the day is something outside the purview of בית דין. Beit
Din. It's between this person and God whether they're sinning or not.
And this person says I know I'm not sinning, I know that
this woman is divorced, I know that the husband died. So therefore
we say actually it's הימנא heimna and we're not going to go
ahead and force them to get divorced because we can't say otherwise.
Okay, so again which is quite interesting because sometimes you know בית
דין Beit Din is not saying look it's just between you and
God. Like if we think let's say I don't know an example,
a husband and wife are living together after we know the wife
committed adultery, right? So I mean not like we do this nowadays,
but in the time of the גמרא Gemara they would basically say
we're going to force the husband to divorce the wife. We're not
going to tolerate the fact that they're living together when they shouldn't
be living together because it's a it's an איסור issur for them
to continue to live together, right? So בית דין Beit Din does
get involved even in preventing people from doing איסורים, issurin, right? But
in this type of a case we don't have objective... knowledge that
they're actually doing איסורין, issurin, right? We just know that it's a
ספק sofek and they're claiming that they're not. So that's an interesting
thing. Even though for us it's a ספק sofek and we should
say you're not allowed to do it on a ספק, sofek, they're
claiming they know the facts, and we don't have direct evidence that
the facts are otherwise, we just have a ספק, sofek, so therefore
we can go ahead and tolerate this situation. Well, he makes a
claim that he knows the facts, she doesn't know.
No, but there's—yeah, well, we're going to get to her in a
minute. Okay, but from the guy's perspective, again, that's the חידוש, chiddush,
he's saying, I know what it is. If we said, we don't
care what you say, we know that it's the other, then we
would intervene. But we don't know it's opposite of what you say.
We have a contradiction. So we're going to go ahead and let
you stay married. Okay, בנישאת לאחד מעדיה. benises l'echad me'edeha.
So the
גמרא Gemara says
הי
גופא באשם תלוי קיימא, hi gufa b'osham taluy kayma, fine, but what
about she? How does she know she's not doing a sin? How
do we tolerate that? So the גמרא Gemara says, באומרת ברי לי.
b'omeres bari li. She says, I also know. Now, of course, if
she says she got a גט, get, she could certainly say ברי
לי. bari li. If she says the husband is dead, how do
we know ברי לי? bari li? So רש"י Rashi says, אין ליבי
נוקפי שברי לי אילו היה קיים היה בא. ein libi nokpi she'bari
li ilu hayah kayam hayah ba. No,
I know my husband, if he were still alive, he would somehow
send word. So again, that's interesting. That is enough for us to
not intervene. Okay, but again, it's only but we as from our
perspective as בית דין beis din only have a ספק. sofek. Right?
We don't have a ודאי. vaday. So we only have a ספק,
sofek, we're not going to intervene if they're, you know, if they're
taking it upon themselves, like essentially that's their business. Okay, which is
again, quite interesting. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב יוחנן. Amar Rav Yochanan. So that's the explanation of
why the רבנים rabbonim say that if she marries we don't have
to do anything. And presumably what the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell out
is about the question about
רב מנחם בר רב יוסי, Rav Menachem bar Rav Yosi, whether when
he says that בדיעבד bedieved if they came afterwards we can let
her stay married, would that also be limited to this type of
a case? That they that she's marrying one of the witnesses and
she says ברי לי bari li and so on, because from the
perspective of the גמרא, Gemara, you know, it raises the question of,
let's say it wasn't that special case, but she got married בהיתר
beheter because there was only the witnesses that said the husband was
dead. She got married בהיתר, beheter, and then the other witnesses came,
and she's not married to one of the witnesses, she's married to
סתם סתם stam stam other guy. So now we have a case
of a ספק, sofek, we would say ואשם תלוי קאי, v'osham taluy
ka'i, but on the other hand she's already married to this other
guy, and maybe she has kids and whatnot, how far would we
take the ספק איסור sofek issur and force them to get divorced
since she had already married בהיתר? beheter? Right? That's what the גמרא
Gemara isn't spelling out.
Maybe depending on whether
she has kids or not... yeah, that's when the husband shows up
and all those things. Here it's שנים נגד שנים. shnayim neged shnayim.
So the גמרא Gemara made a special case to allow her to
get married to sort of when she got married after the contradictory
witnesses had come. But if she got married before the contradictory where
then we're saying she can stay married, maybe we would even allow
a broader range of cases in that case because she's already married,
and at the end of the day we only have a ספק
sofek what her status is. Yes.
The question about the possibility of self-interest on the witness's part because
he wants to marry her?
Yeah, so that's also a very good question, right? Why don't we
say very convenient, right? You got on the witness stand and say
the husband is dead and then you wind up marrying the wife.
I know, that has always really really that has always really shocked
me, you know, that that doesn't make us suspicious about that. Yeah.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב
ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, where are we?
אמר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan, yes.
אמר רב יוחנן שנים אומרים מת ושנים אומרים לא מת הרי זו
לא תינשא ואם נישאת לא תצא.
Amar Rav Yochanan shnayim omrim
meis v'shnayim omrim lo meis harei zu lo tinasei v'im nises lo
tetzei.
So we've already said that according to the חכמים chachamim don't get
married, but if you got married don't get divorced, which now we've
explained it to be a case of נישאת לאחד מעדיה nises l'echad
me'edeha is how we've explained that. Okay now, ואם נישאת לא תצא.
שנים אומרים נתגרשה ושנים אומרים לא נתגרשה הרי זו לא תינשא ואם
נישאת תצא. V'im nises lo tetzei. Shnayim omrim nisgarsha v'shnayim omrim lo
nisgarsha harei zu lo tinasei v'im nises tetzei.
So now we're saying a different פסק. psak. When it comes to
two say divorced and two say not divorced, then she does have
to go out from the second marriage, even if she בדיעבד bedieved
married the guy afterwards. Why is it different? I mean if it's
a case about נישאת לאחד מעדיה, nises l'echad me'edeha, you know, the
whole type of a thing, why should this be any different than
the previous case? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא רישא
ומאי שנא סיפא? mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa? How's it different?
אמר אביי תרגמה בעד אחד. Amar Abaye targema b'eid echad.
So he says, no, no, no, it's a special case. It's not
two against two, it's one against one. So how does one against
one marry matter? עד אחד אומר מת, eid echad omer meis, if
one says died and one says not died. So now we're really
back to יבמות Yevamos world.
So עד אחד אומר מת, eid echad omer meis, so that case
הימנוהו רבנן כבי תרי. heimnuhu rabonon k'bei trei. So remember in יבמות
Yevamos one עד eid said the husband died, he's treated like two.
וכדרבי עולא דאמר עולא כל מקום שהאמינה תורה
עד אחד הרי כאן שנים. u'chiderabi Ulla d'amar Ulla kol makom shehe'emina
Torah eid echad harei kan shnayim. Whenever the Torah or here we're
talking about the רבנן rabbonim here, but anyway, whenever the Torah believes
one witness, he's treated as two. Okay, so one witness says the
husband is dead, the special הלכה halacha of יבמות Yevamos of believing
that the husband is dead gives that one witness the weight of
two. והאי דאמר לא מת, v'hai d'amar lo meis, and now one
witness afterwards said he didn't die. So now that one witness who
said didn't die only has the weight of one, right? A witness
who said the husband... die equals is the weight of two. A
witness who says the husband didn't die only has the weight of
one. So that's a question. It might only be if it happened
if he came afterwards. That's discussed in the גמרא Gemara and in
תוספות Tosafot and whatever. Yes. והאי דקאמר לא מית הוי ליה חד
ואין דבריו של אחד במקום שנים. veha dikamar lo meis havi lei
chad ve'ein devarav shel echad bimkom shenayim.
So that's why when it's one against one, not two against two,
but one against one, it's then one against one becomes as if
one against two. And in that case actually we believe that the
husband is dead. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi,
if that's true, because of the rules of testimony about the dead
husband, we believe the one that said dead over the one that
said not dead. So if that's true אפילו לכתחילה נמי afilu l'chatchila
nami we should לכתחילה l'chatchila let her marry somebody else. Why do
we say לכתחילה l'chatchila not? So it says you know what, in
principle you're right. But משום דרבי אסי, mishum d'Rabbi Assi, but it's
because of what רבי אסי Rabbi Assi says, דאמר רבי אסי, d'amar
Rabbi Assi, הסר ממך עקשות פה ולזות שפתים הרחק ממך, haser mimcha
ikshus peh velazus sefasayim harchek mimcha, remove from yourself the perversion of
the mouth
and like the you know the report like the the rumor of
lips you should distance from you. Don't give people sort of you
know gossiping about you. If it's one against one, you know people
will be very suspicious, so you shouldn't do it. Of course I
would say if you're marrying אחד מעדיה, echad me'edeha, it would also
be very suspicious, but okay. Anyway, that's how we explain why you
are allow her to stay married, and and maybe even in principle
she could לכתחילה l'chatchila marry the other guy because it's one against
one and it's about the dead husband. So there's special believability that
he's dead. As opposed to סיפא seifa in the end, עד אחד
אומר נתגרשה ועד אחד אומר לא נתגרשה, ed echad omer nisgareshah ve'ed
echad omer lo nisgareshah, one says divorced and one says not divorced,
תרווייהו באשת איש קמסדקי, traivaihu b'eishes ish kamsahadei, they're both conceding that
she was a married woman. והאי דאמר נתגרשה הוי ליה חד ואין
דבריו של אחד במקום שנים, veha d'amar nisgareshah havi lei chad ve'ein
devarav shel echad bimkom shenayim, and you only have one witness that
this married woman is divorced, so that one witness is not worth
anything. So in that case even if she got married, she has
to leave the guy she married because you have you don't even
have a ספק. safek. Effectively you have knowledge that she was an
אשת איש eishes ish and an עד אחד ed echad that she
was divorced, which is worthless. Okay, so in that case
that's why we
had no חידוש—well, chiddush right. Once we made it a case of
עד אחד, ed echad, it's no חידוש chiddush that she
has to—that she has to תצא.
teizei. Right. So that's one way of explaining it. When it's two
against two we would say בדיעבד לא תצא, bedieved lo teizei, but
when it's one against one and it's a case about גירושין, gerushin,
then of course the testimony of that she's נתגרשה nisgareshah is worthless
and we're going to say תצא. teizei.
What was the what was the אפילו לכתחילה afilu l'chatchila lines about?
Yeah, if it's one against one and by the testimony of the
husband is dead we believe the guy who said dead more than
the guy who said didn't dead, he's the one believed, then why
don't we לכתחילה l'chatchila let her marry another guy? Why is it
only בדיעבד bedieved if she gets married she can stay married? So
the גמרא Gemara says yes, you're right. In principle הלכתית halachically לכתחילה
l'chatchila she could, but you know we don't—it doesn't look good. Okay,
רבי אסי. Rabbi Assi. So now that's one explanation, it was one
against one, that's the difference between גירושין gerushin and מיתה. misah. Let's
do the other explanation. רבא אמר לעולם תרי ותרי נינהו. Rava amar
l'olam terei v'terei ninhu.
No, no, no. It's like it says, two against two. So what's
the difference between גירושין gerushin and מיתה? misah? וסבר רבי יוחנן דרב
מנחם ברבי יוסי בגירושין ולא סבר במיתה. vesavar Rabbi Yochanan d'Rav Menachem
berabbi Yossi begerushin velo savar bemisah. רב
מנחם ברבי יוסי
Rav Menachem
berabbi Yossi says that even בדיעבד bedieved she has to get divorced.
He was persuaded by that argument when it came to testimony about
the גט, get, but not testimony about the death. מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? מיתה אינה יכולה להכחישו. misah einah yecholah lehachchisho. When if
they're saying the husband died, she better know feel really confident that
the husband is dead, because if the husband shows up, what's she
going to say? Right? This was issues we had in יבמות, Yevamos,
right? The woman really makes sure she knows what she's doing. So
in that case בדיעבד bedieved if she gets married, we'll let her
stay married, because we'll figure she probably she you know she's probably
pretty confident that that's the case. גירושין יכולה להכחישו. gerushin yecholah lehachchisho.
But by גט, get, if the husband showed up and says I
never divorced you, she could always say, "Yes, you did." Right? So
therefore in the גט get case, two against two, we're not going
to let her stay married because in that case, you know, once
certainly when the two came before she married, we're not going to
let her stay married because we can really be suspicious suspect that
maybe it that maybe she it didn't happen and she's not and
she's prepared to take the risk because it's really not much of
a risk.
So even without a גט get she can just say you know
I'm divorced, she'd be believed?
Well, there were witnesses that she had a גט. get. It's just
two against two. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara just to end this
off, the גמרא Gemara says ומי חציפא כולי האי? umi chatzipah kulei
hai? Would she be so חוצפה'דיק chutzpadik to contradict brazenly contradict her
husband? ואמר רב המנונא האשה שאמרה לבעלה גרשתני נאמנת. ve'amar Rav Hamnuna
ha'ishah she'amerah leba'alah gerashtani ne'emenes. A woman who said to her husband
without a גט, get, "You divorced me," she's believed. חזקה אין אשה
מעיזה פניה בפני בעלה. chazakah ein ishah me'izah paneha bifnei ba'alah. A
woman would never be so brazen to say this to her husband
without a גט. get. So here too we should say she would
not be so brazen and therefore we should believe her that she
is actually, you know, knows what she's talking about. גמרא Gemara says
no, הני מילי היכא דליכא סהדי. hani mili heicha d'leika sahadei.
That's when there are no witnesses
ודקמסייע לה, v'dekamsayiah lah, there aren't witnesses that support her. אבל היכא
דאיכא סהדי דקמסייע לה, aval heicha d'ika sahadei d'kamsayiah lah, מיעזא ומיעזא.
me'aza u'me'aza. When there are witnesses that support her, she is willing
to be brazen. So basically what the גמרא Gemara says is we
have the debate about two against two. The חכמים Chachamim say don't
get married, but if you're married you don't have to get divorced.
רב מנחם ברבי יוסי Rav Menachem berabbi Yossi even after married you
have to get divorced because it remains a ספק, sofek, and now
we have a split between גירושין geirushin and נישואין nisuin what the
difference is. So one explanation was one against one which made it
a special case, but in the explanation two against two, the difference
is do we let them stay married afterwards? In the case by
מיתה, misa, we say yes because we're less concerned that she's lying
because there's no way she's going to get out of it, or
we're more concerned that she clarified the situation or she's
more believed, right, because there's a bigger risk, so that case בדיעבד
bidi'eved we'll let her stay married, whereas by גט get there's really
no risk, so even בדיעבד bidi'eved we won't let her stay married.
Okay.
Are the two witnesses also lying? What? Are the two witnesses lying?
It's saying there's two against two.